<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. William Ladson, Junior, at Tichmarsh in the county of Northampton by William Sheppard ...</title>
            <author>Sheppard, William, d. 1675?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13282637</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13282637</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98775</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59748)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98775)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 439:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. William Ladson, Junior, at Tichmarsh in the county of Northampton by William Sheppard ...</title>
                  <author>Sheppard, William, d. 1675?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. 28.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ladson, William.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LV, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98775:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:98775:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL OF Mr. <hi>William Ladſon</hi> Junior, AT TICHMARSH In the County of NORTHAMPTON.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Sheppard,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1694.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98775:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98775:2"/>
            <head>A Funeral Sermon, on <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 55. 6. <hi>Seek ye the Lord while he may be found, call ye upon him while he is near.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THIS Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is called the Evangelical Prophet; indeed he Propheſies clearly of Jeſus Chriſt: In the 53d Chapter he ſpeaks of the Sufferings of Chriſt, as if they had been already paſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7. The whole Chapter ſpeaks of Chriſt, and his Sufferings. In this Chapter where is the Text, he makes a free invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> to come in to Chriſt:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ho]</hi> it is a note of Compellation, and of Invitation:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every one]</hi> whether <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> v. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That thirſteth]</hi> that is in diſtreſs, and being ſenſible of his diſtreſſed Condition, is deſirous of relief; for theſe things concur in thirſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41. 17, 18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come]</hi> the word ſignifies either go, or come; here it is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred come, becauſe they are called to return to God whom before they had forſaken, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the waters]</hi> that is, to the waters of Saving Grace and Spiritual Comfort which Chriſt brings: <hi>John</hi> 4. 10. 14. it is like our Saviour's invitation to come to him with aſſurance of finding relief from him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. 37, 38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And he that hath no Money]</hi> no Silver, no Merits; but Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits none can have; The meaning is, He that is never ſo poor, that hath nothing of any worth or valuable conſideration; implying, <hi>that Chriſt and Grace are given freely,</hi> Rom. 3. 24. Epheſ. 2. 8. And here in the Text the Prophet makes an exhortation and call to all unconverted ones to come in, and make their peace while they may, while God makes gracious offers, and tenders of Grace, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98775:3"/>
               <hi>Seek ye the Lord]</hi> as implying, that they had left him, and were fallen out of favour by their ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>While he may be found]</hi> in a time of acceptance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 8. while he offereth himſelf unto you in the means of grace, in the Miniſtry of the word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 7. before the time of repenting be expired, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 3. before God grow weary of forbearing, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44. 22. and he take a Solemn Oath that he will not be found, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. 11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 15. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 24, to 28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Call ye upon him while he is near,]</hi> that is, while he cometh near unto you, in his Ordinances, by his Miniſters and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. 5. My Righteouſneſs is near, that is, in the Miniſtry of his word, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 17. Now Chriſt comes and preacheth peace to you, offers peace to you in the Miniſtry of his Goſpel: Therefore <hi>now ſeek him while he may be found, call upon him while he is near.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That it is the Great Concern of Souls to get a Chriſt while they may.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is our Great Concerning Work, to get a Chriſt while he is to be had. There are ſome Doctrines that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern ſome, but not others; that may concern the Rich, but not the Poor; or the Poor, but not the Rich: the Old, but not the Young: But this is a Doctrine that concerns all, Rich, and Poor, Old, and Young. It is the great Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all, Rich and Poor, Old and Young, to <hi>ſeek a Chriſt while he is to be found:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> I. Becauſe we are all utterly loſt, and undone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him. We may be without Friends, without Houſes or Lands, without Money, without Riches, without Health, yea Life it ſelf, and yet be happy; but we cannot be without a Chriſt, but we muſt be miſerable, undone for ever, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>We are all by Nature Children of wrath:</hi> This is thy Condition, that readeſt theſe Lines: if thou art ſtill in thy natural ſtate, thou art under the wrath of God, and how doſt thou think to bear it? His Wrath rends the Rocks, and makes the Mountains tremble, <hi>Nahum</hi> 1. 5, 6. Thou art a Sinner by nature, and by practice.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98775:3"/>
1. A Sinner by Nature, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51. 5. We are no ſooner warm in the Womb, but we are Sinners: This makes Sin natural to thee: It is rooted in thy Nature; as Poyſon in a Toad; that thou canſt do nothing but Sin, ſo long as thou art in thy unconverted State, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Sinner by Practice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thy Heart is full of Sin, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 9. Thy Heart is not only wicked, but deſperately wicked; and if thou ſeeſt it not; it is, becauſe thou art born Blind, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 19. See what wickedneſs is in thy Heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thy Life is full of Sin: 1. Sinful Thoughts, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 5.</p>
            <p>God ſaw that the wickedneſs of Man was great: And why? Becauſe every Imagination of the Thoughts of his Heart was only evil continually. This is wickedneſs indeed; when all the Imaginations, and Thoughts, and Purpoſes and Deſires are Evil, not partly good, and partly evil, but only evil; and not evil ſometime, and good ſometime, but evil alway: Evil continually. Doſt thou not ſee what a Sinner thou art? Is not this a miſerable Condition thou art in?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sinful Words,</hi> Idle Words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 36, 37. Theſe are ſuch, thou canſt not ſtand before God at Judgment for: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides wicked prophane Words, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 12. 4. Jam. 3. 6. here is a World of Iniquity, ſet on fire of Hell.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Sinful Actions:</hi> How many are the Commiſſions of Evil? Omiſſions of Good? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 23. As to the Sabbath, thou mayſt ſee how thou haſt ſinned, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 13. <hi>Speaking thy own Words, doing thy own Pleaſure.</hi> For Week days, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable have been thy evil Thoughts, and Words, and Actions, though thou haſt not ſeen them? Every day you have gone without Prayer, you have ſinned: 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>Pray without ceaſing:</hi> Not that we ſhould do nothing elſe but pray; Yes, we are to follow our Callings too: But it is to be our daily practice: We are to Pray daily, as well as Plow daily, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. <hi>laſt.</hi> You may profeſs that you are Chriſtians, and are Baptized; but God reckons you among the Heathen, if you do not pray; and will pour out his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry upon you. O the innumerable Evils which compaſs you about, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 40. 12. Then Death follows upon Sin. <hi>The Soul that Sins, it ſhall dye,</hi> Ezek. 18. 4. God ſaith, thou art a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98775:4"/>
Dead Man, a Damned Man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12. Death comes upon all that have ſinned, therefore this is thy Caſe: <hi>Firſt,</hi> Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 27. But this is not all. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Worſe ſtill, Spiritual death, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1, 12. You are dead in Sin, without God, without Chriſt: without the ſaving Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God: without the Life of God: without Sence of God: without the Enjoyment of God: You are under the Power of Sin, and no Sence of it: Under the Wrath of God, and no fear, nor feeling of it: Doth the reading of theſe Lines make thee fear, and feel? This would be thy Mercy: To be every moment liable to Damnation, and no trouble about it, this is ſad. And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This is worſe ſtill, thou art liable to Eternal Death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23. <hi>The wages of Sin is Death:</hi> But what Death? The ſecond Death: But what is this ſecond Death? you may ſee it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 14. The ſecond Death is the Lake of Fire. Is it not a dreadful thing to lie in a Lake of Fire? <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 41. It is Everlaſting Fire with the Devil and damned ones: Is not this a miſerable Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on indeed? And as ſure as God is true, this is thy Caſe, who readeſt theſe Lines, out of Chriſt: And doſt thou not ſee it to be thy great Concernment, to get a Chriſt while he is to be had?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe Jeſus is the only Remedy out of this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and wretched State.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Jeſus Chriſt is the Remedy.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) God the Father did purpoſe from Eternity to ſave Sinners by Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19, 20. Therefore Jeſus Chriſt is a Remedy, for he was ordained from Eternity to redeem with his precious Blood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 8.</p>
            <p n="2">(2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) There was a voluntary Compact and Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God the Father and Chriſt: God the Father was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to give Chriſt to be the ranſom of the Elect; and Chriſt the Son of God preſented himſelf moſt willing to procure that Salvation for them; the Father promiſed him a ſpiritual Kingdom and Seed, upon his dying for them; and the Son came up to this, and ſaid, <hi>Lo I come, I delight to do thy Will,</hi> Pſalm 40. 7, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Chriſt was promiſed unto <hi>Adam,</hi> Gen. 3. 15.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) The Legal Sacrifices and Offerings did typifie Jeſus
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98775:4"/>
Chriſt, offering himſelf, ſhedding his Blood to take away Sin, and make Peace; as is ſhewed in the <hi>Hebrews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Jeſus Chriſt did actually come and preſent himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World to be a Redeemer, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4, 5.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) Jeſus did really execute the Office of a Mediatour, did fulfil all Righteouſneſs, give himſelf a Ranſom, and by his Blood reconcile, and make Peace, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 19, 20, 21, 22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As Jeſus Chriſt is the Remedy, ſo Jeſus Chriſt is the only Remedy, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>There is one God, and one Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour between God and Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Acts 4. 12. <hi>Neither is there Salvation in any other.</hi> Chriſt only was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God the Father, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. 1. Chriſt only was ſent, and ſealed, <hi>John</hi> 6. 27. On Chriſt was laid our Iniquities, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 6. Chriſt only was qualified for the Office of a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour, and Redeemer. Three things muſt be in him, who doth this Office, which are only to be found in Chriſt:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> He muſt not be of the number of thoſe who are to be redeemed: Therefore no ſimple Man can be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He muſt be of the Nature of thoſe who are to be redeemed: He muſt be of the ſame Seed with them; and therefore no Angel can redeem, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He muſt be more than a meer Creature; for a meer Creature cannot ſatisfie, nor can his Righteouſneſs be imputed to another; and he muſt be able to overcome Sin, and Death, and raiſe himſelf, which no Creature can do; therefore neither Men, nor Angels can be Redeemers, none but Jeſus Chriſt: Thus (Reader) thou ſeeſt the ſecond Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why thou art greatly concerned to get a Chriſt, becauſe he is the only Remedy out of thy miſerable State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. It is our great Concernment to get a Chriſt while he is to be had, becauſe there will be a time when he will not be had: Therefore the Text ſaith, <hi>Seek him, while he may be found,</hi> implying, that there will be a time, when he will not be found.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It will be, that time will be at an end: Then there can be no ſeeking, therefore there can be no finding. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 29, 30, 31. <hi>The Time is ſhort,</hi> which implies, it will have an end; therefore, ſaith he, uſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98775:5"/>
the World, as if you uſed it not; ſeek the things of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World; get a Chriſt before this ſhort time is ended. There was a miſerable Inſtance I knew, one that on the Death-bed cried out moſt hideouſly, Call Time again; Call Time again: But there is no calling Time again, when once it is gone; O therefore, lay about you, to get a Chriſt while he is to be had, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2. The Apoſtle ſaith, [Now,] he doth not ſay, [To Morrow,] hereafter; <hi>But now is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted Time, now is the Day of Salvation:</hi> Therefore look out for a Chriſt now: This is the Voice of dying ones, look for a Chriſt now: get a Chriſt before time is gone.</p>
            <p>This was the Voice of this Young Man Deceaſed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired that this Text might be preached on at his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, that Young Ones eſpecially might be called upon, and warned to ſeek a Chriſt while he is to be found. He la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the breach of Promiſes with God; this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Caſe of Young Ones to be making good Reſolutions to ſeek God, turn to God, get into Chriſt; and afterwards to fall off from them: The Lord was pleaſed to make this Young Man ſenſible of it, and (we hope) effectually brought him to Chriſt, and gave him Repentance and Pardon, and ſome comfortable Evidences of it; as appeared by his chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful yielding and reſigning himſelf up to the Lord in the laſt Agony of Death, with theſe Words, That He would now throw himſelf into a full Fountain; and immediately, he gave up the Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Life will be at an end, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>Your Life is but as a vapour, which is but for a little time, and then vaniſheth away:</hi> Therefore get a Chriſt now ſpeedily, before this vapour of Life vaniſh away. Great <hi>Tamberlain</hi> was carried away with a Fit of an Ague, while he was in expectation of the Conqueſt of the <hi>Othoman</hi> Family, and <hi>Greek</hi> Empire. Therefore take heed, leſt, while you are purſuing great things here, Life doth end before you have got a Chriſt. This is the call of dying ones; Life is going. O get a Chriſt before Life is ended, <hi>John.</hi> 9. 4. O get a Chriſt, while Life laſteth; the night of Death cometh, when no Man can Work: There is no working in the Grave, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 10. Therefore what you find to do, do with your might: And Chriſt tells you, <hi>Joh.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98775:5"/>
6. 29. <hi>This is the Work of God, that ye believe in him whom he hath ſent.</hi> Art thou a young One, that readeſt theſe Lines; God calls upon thee to work with thy might to get a Chriſt, becauſe the night of Death is coming, when thou canſt not Work.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Opportunity will be at an end. Opportunity may be ſhorter than Life: We read of ſome, that in the time of their Life, the things of their Peace were hid from their Eyes, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 42. Chriſt weeps over them: This is a dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Caſe; Reader, take heed, it be not thy Caſe: Now Chriſt offers himſelf to thee; take heed thou doſt not by thy refuſals cauſe Chriſt to hide himſelf from thee before thy Life be ended. It is ſaid of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> that when he could have taken <hi>Rome,</hi> he would not; but when he would, he could not. O therefore take him while you may: God ſaith, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 3. <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alway ſtrive with Man;</hi> it is wonderful Mercy, it ſtrives with you now: O take heed of loſing this ſtriving time: Chriſt tells us, this ſhall be the Caſe of them; and they ſhall ſeek him, when it is too late, <hi>John</hi> 8. 21. <hi>Ye ſhall ſeek me, and ſhall die in your Sins.</hi> Now you may ſeek, and live: Then you will ſeek, and dye too: Chriſt foretels by the Parable of the Fooliſh Virgins, that ſome will come, when the Door is ſhut, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 8, 10, 11, 12. Give us Oyl, give us Chriſt; but it was too late. Reader, art thou Old, or Young, if thou doſt not get a Chriſt now, this will be thy cry, when it is too late; Lord, give me Chriſt; Lord, give me Mercy; Lord, now I will let my Sins go; now I will be Godly: No, then it will be too late; the Door is ſhut; Mercy is gone; Chriſt is gone; his Bowels of Mercy are ſhut up for ever: Take him, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, let him burn, and roar; cry, and howl in Hell for ever: O how this will torment the Soul to think that it had an opportunity, and it is gone, and gone for ever; it ſhall never have offer of a Chriſt, nor Mercy, more for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Terrour to Sinners that come not to Chriſt: Soul, is it thy great Concernment to come in to Chriſt whilſt thou mayſt, and wilt thou not come? Is Time going, and Life going, and Opportunity going, and wilt thou not have Chriſt while thou mayſt? How inexcuſable wilt thou be in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98775:6"/>
the Day of God? What is it that hinders thy coming? I muſt tell thee, that whatſoever it is, that thou makeſt an hinderance, it will not excuſe thee.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is it Ignorance? This is one thing that keeps Souls from Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 2. <hi>They ſee no Beauty in him, that they ſhould deſire him,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 8. But this will be no excuſe: God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that he will not ſave them that know him not: Nay, he will damn them; this will aggravate their Miſery, that there is a Chriſt, but they neglect to know him: Flaming Fire will be their Portion, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 8, 9. Children, labour to know Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doth ſpiritual ſloth keep thee off from Jeſus Chriſt? This keeps off many: If Chriſt were to be had with a wet Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; with a good wiſh; with a Lord have Mercy upon him; or a cold Prayer now and then; many would have him: But Chriſt tells us, that the Kingdom of Heaven ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers violence, and the violent take it by force, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 12. There muſt be crying, and crying mightily; ſtriving, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wreſtling, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 24. And Chriſt gives this Reaſon, why few have him. <hi>Becauſe ſtrait is the Gate, and narrow the way,</hi> Mat. 7. 14. But this will not excuſe, but aggravate their Condition; becauſe they take great pains for other things, for things of no worth for the Soul: If men took half the Pains for a Chriſt, as they do for the World, they might have him: But how will this torment in Hell, that they took more Pains to damn, than to ſave themſelves?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love of Sin, and the World, keeps many Souls from Chriſt: Chriſt offers himſelf, but Men go to their Farms, Merchandiſe; and make Light of him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 5. They are ſo buſie about Plowing, and Sowing; and buying, and ſelling; that they have no leiſure to attend to the ſeeking of a Chriſt. If God and the World might dwell together, if Sin and Chriſt might part Stakes, then Chriſt would have many followers: But Chriſt tells us, <hi>That he that Loves Houſe or Land, Father or Mother, Wife or Children, or his own Life more than him cannot be his Diſciple,</hi> Luke 14. 26, 27, 33. Ah Souls! take heed that none of theſe things keep you off from Jeſus Chriſt; for how will this torment in Hell, to think, that you loſt Chriſt, and Heaven, for the World, that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98775:6"/>
cannot at laſt countervail? <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 26. Nor procure a drop of Water to cool your Tongue, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 22, 23, 24, 25.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Carnal Mirth and Pleaſure keep many off from Chriſt: They think if they come in to Chriſt, they muſt bid farewel to their merry Company, and jovial Ways; and this they do not like of: But this is but a fooliſh Plea; for Chriſt doth not hinder a Man of any pleaſures that are good for him; and if he deprives thee of ſinful Pleaſures, he will give thee ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Pleaſures, Soul Pleaſures, which will be infinitely better; here you ſhall find his ways to be ways of pleaſantneſs, and paths of Peace, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 17. Rom. 15. 13. <hi>Joy and Peace in believing: Yea Joy unſpeakable, and full of Glory,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 8. And beſides all this, Everlaſting Pleaſures hereafter, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 16. 11. Who then would not have a Chriſt? You young Ones, who are for Pleaſures, come in to Chriſt, come, O come, other Pleaſures are not worth having: See what <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> the wiſeſt ſaith of them, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 2, 6. Why wilt thou ſet thine eyes on that which is not? It is not that which it ſeems to be, it is but madneſs: I ſaid of laughter thou art mad, and of mirth, what doth it? What doth it? I will tell you what it doth: It doth infatuate, it doth bewitch, it doth delude Souls, it decoys them into the net of woe and miſery: It is as the crackling of thorns under a Pot; it makes a great ſound for a moment, and then ends in Eternal ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50. 11. <hi>Amos.</hi> 8. 10. <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 25. <hi>Woe to you that laugh now, for ye ſhall mourn and weep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Security and falſe peace keeps many from Chriſt: Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, doth not this keep thee? Thou doſt not come to Chriſt becauſe thou art ſecure in thy ſins, thou doſt not ſee thy need of him, or elſe thou wouldeſt cry after him, and have no reſt night nor day; thou art like <hi>Laodicea,</hi> thou thinkeſt thy ſelf rich, and ſtandeſt in need of nothing, when thou art poor, blind, miſerable, wretched, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 17. thou ſeeſt no need of Chriſt, though thou haſt infinite need of him, and the more peace thou haſt, the greater danger thou art in, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 3. When they cry peace, and ſafety, then ſudden deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction comes upon them, and they ſhall not eſcape. Mark Reader, then is thy danger, when thou cryeſt, Peace, peace, then is the time that deſtruction cometh. As it is with a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98775:7"/>
Man that hath the Falling Sickneſs, he talks, and walks, and is very merry and jovial, as if nothing ail'd him, of a ſudden he falls down upon the ground, foams and raves, and beats himſelf, and is a miſerable Spectacle to all beholders: Juſt thus it is with ſecure Sinners, Reader, take heed it be not thy caſe,) they eat, and drink, and ſleep quietly, talk mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and walk about jocundly, plow, and ſow, buy, and ſell, are very buſie about the World, of a ſudden Death comes, and ſtrikes them down dead; immediately they fall into Hell, and there are crying and roaring, ſcrieching and howling, curſing and banning; Oh! hath my ſecure God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs life brought me hither? Hath my falſe peace brought me hither? Is this the end of my Chriſtleſs, Prayerleſs Life? O that I had ſpent all my days and nights in the World in mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for my ſins, crying for a Chriſt! O that I had been a Dog, or a Toad, then, when I had dyed, my miſery had been ended; but now this is but the beginning of my woe, which will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver end. Man, Woman, Child, that readeſt theſe Lines, do theſe things affect thy heart, and bring thee down at the foot of Chriſt? O labour to do now, as thou wilt then wiſh that thou hadſt done, or as damned Souls now wiſh that they had done.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Deluding Hopes: Now the Word tells Men, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters tell them of their danger, and call upon them to ſeek a Chriſt, repent, believe, be godly; but they flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and they have ſometimes ſome convictions and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in their Souls, but they lick themſelves whole with falſe hopes; we hope we may be ſaved without ſo much adoe, God is merciful, Chriſt dyed for Sinners: Is not this thycaſe, thou that readeſt theſe lines? Know thou, that theſe are but vain hopes, as long as thou art out of Chriſt, and theſe hopes of thine will fail thee: Hear what God ſaith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it: It is not I, but God that ſpeaks it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11. 7. When a wicked Man dyeth, his expectation ſhall periſh: And the hope of unjuſt Men periſheth: Hear this Sinner, old, or young; thou mayſt keep thy falſe hope as long as thou liveſt, but thou canſt keep it no longer, <hi>Job.</hi> 11. 20. The eyes of the Wicked ſhall fail, and they ſhall not eſcape, and their hope ſhall be as the giving up of the ghoſt: O what terrour this ſpeaks to Chriſtleſs Souls! The giving up of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98775:7"/>
ghoſt is ſudden, in a moment; ſo theſe falſe hopes, when Death comes, ſhall be gone in a moment: The Life is not given up without great pain, ſo when theſe falſe hopes are gone, the Soul will be full of horrour, the Soul and Body part, and never meet here more to live in this World; ſo then Sinners loſe their hopes, and ſhall never have hope more. Then Oh what cries and howlings will there be, that the hopes are gone, and gone for ever! Oh the cries and howlings! I was told of this, but I mad wretch would not believe it; but I ſee now I am moſt miſerable: Now I have no hope of a dram of Mercy for ever. As it was with <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram, Numb.</hi> 16. 31, 32, 33, 34. <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> fled at their cry, when they went down into the Pit. It is now with Men and Women as it was with them in the days of <hi>Noah, Mat.</hi> 24. 37, 38, 39. <hi>They were eating, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, marrying, 'till Noah entred into the Ark, and the floud came, and took them all away. Noah</hi> was a Preacher of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, moved with fear, prepared an Ark, gave them warning, but they would not take warning; what cryes do you think there were when the Floud came? Then they would have got into the Ark, but could not, they might climb upon Trees or Mountains, but all in vain. Sinners are now warned by the preachers of the word to get into the Ark Chriſt, but will not: Oh then the horror, when the deluge of miſery overflows them! I might have had the Ark Chriſt, and would not. What cries were there in <hi>Sodom</hi> when the Storm of Brimſtone and Fire came upon them! Oh the cries and howlings when you are tormented with fire and brimſtone in Hell! Oh mad Wretch! I was offered a Chriſt, and I would not! Now you ſay, let us ſay what we will, you will hope; if it were not for hope, the heart would break; now your falſe hopes keep your hearts whole; but then your hearts will break in pieces, and break for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2. Be Exhorted then to get a Chriſt while you may. To the Old. To the Young.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the Old: You are greatly concern'd to get a Chriſt, you cannot have much time before you, you have one foot in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98775:8"/>
the Grave, therefore you have need to beſtir you, <hi>Ecl.</hi> 11. 8. If a Man live many years, and rejoice in them all, yet let him remember the days of darkneſs, for they ſhall be many. The days of darkneſs which follow, ſhall be more than the years of joy which went before, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7. 9, 10. It is ſaid of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> Strangers have devoured his ſtrength, and he knoweth it not; yea, gray hairs are here and there upon him, yet he knoweth not. And they do not return to the Lord, nor ſeek him for all this. Oh what a wretched thing is this! Strange luſts, ſtrange practices, ſtrange ways are found with him: Gray hairs, Old Age is found with him, yet he conſiders it no, What an Old Man, and a graceleſs Man; an Old Man, and yet a prayerleſs Man, and yet not ſeek the Lord for a Chriſt! What a vile thing is this? what a miſerable condition is this? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 20. The Sinner, being an hundred years old ſhall be accurſed: What a miſerable caſe is this, for a Man to have many years given him to get a Chriſt in, and yet at laſt dye Chriſtleſs; he muſt needs be curſed.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Alexander</hi> Beſieged a City, he was wont to ſet up an inch of Candle, and if they came in, and made their peace in that time, well and good, if not, there was no quarter for them: Juſt ſo it is here with you, Old Men, you have an inch of time given you to get a Chriſt, and Mercy; if you now get a Chriſt, make your peace with God while this inch of time laſts, happy are you; but if not, there is no peace to be made for you, no Chriſt to be had, nor mercy for ever. O therefore, as you love your Souls, cloſe in with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's Councel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 7. <hi>To day, if you will hear his voice, harden not your hearts.</hi> This is the voice of God to you; get a Chriſt to day: Chriſt offers himſelf to you, if you will take him, take him to day; cry to God for him; and if you do not, it is the hardneſs of your hearts: And that is an hard heart indeed, that will not have a Chriſt, when offered to him, though he muſt be damned for ever without him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaid, Whether I eat, or drink, or ſleep, methinks I hear the Trumpet ſound, <hi>Ariſe ye dead and come to Judgment.</hi> Old ones, let this awaken you, to ſet to your work ſpeedily, and ply it in good earneſt day and night, to get a Chriſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98775:8"/>
while you may, and account it infinite mercy, that it is not too late.</p>
            <p>2. To the Young: Now the Lord ſpeaks to you, labour to get a Chriſt while you may.</p>
            <p>Eccleſ. 12. 1. <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy Youth;</hi> remember to get Chriſt now in thy Youth: God ſaith, [Now] do not drive it off 'till hereafter: If you will have a Chriſt take him now, before the evil days come; Old Age is called evil days, when you will not be ſo fit to ſeek him: Now you are more fit to read the Scriptures, than when your eyes are dim, and you cannot ſee: Now you are more fit to pray, than when your knees are ſtiff, and will not bend, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 6, 7, 8, 9. God ſends thee to the Ant to get Wiſdom: The Ant Provides her meat in the Summer againſt Winter; thy youth is thy Summer, if thou wilt have a Chriſt, get him now in thy youth, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11. 9. <hi>Rejoyce, O Young Man, in thy Youth, and let thine heart chear thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ſight of thine eyes, and in the way of thine heart, but know thou, that for theſe things God will bring thee into Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God by this Ironical expreſſion would turn young ones hearts from their ſins to himſelf: As if God had ſaid, Young Men, if you think it your beſt way to go on in your ſins, and to walk in the ways of your own hearts, go on, but be it at your own peril; for, know ye, that I will bring you to Judgment for all your ways and doings: Conſider how you ſhall be able to ſtand before me in judgment, for theſe ways you now walk in, and how you ſhall come off in that day. There will be no ſtanding for you without a Chriſt in that day. Art thou a young one, that readeſt theſe lines? then remember that now is thy time to get a Chriſt, but it may be, Satan, and thy Companions tell thee, thou art young, and needeſt not trouble thy ſelf about theſe things yet, but mayeſt follow thy pleaſures, and have time enough to get a Chriſt ſeven years hence; mark what God ſays to this, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27. 1. Boaſt not thy ſelf of to morrow, <hi>for thou knoweſt not what a day may bring forth.</hi> If you will have a Chriſt, take him to day, make ſure of him to day, go and cry to God for him to night, thou knoweſt not but thou mayeſt be in Hell before to morrow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98775:9"/>
Remember the Man in the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 19, 20. who talked of many years, but God ſaid to him, <hi>Thou Fool, this Night ſhall thy Soul be required of thee.</hi> Oh, it is folly and madneſs to put off the getting of Chriſt 'till to morrow. There is great danger in delaying.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a certain danger: You, that are the youngeſt, are every moment liable to the ſtroke of Death. You may talk of living many years, but what is your life but a <hi>Vapour that appeareth but for a little time, and then vaniſheth away,</hi> James 4. 13, 14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here may be ſudden danger, <hi>Job</hi> 21. 13. They ſpend their days in Wealth, in Mirth, and in a moment go down to the Grave: Young ones, conſider this ſeriouſly, what a dangerous thing it is to be Chriſtleſs, you may live in mirth, and pleaſure, and have nothing trouble you, but this doth not ſecure you from the grave; Death comes of a ſudden, and knocks you down, and you fall down in a moment, not only into the Grave, but if you be Chriſtleſs, into Hell-fire, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 3. when they ſhall ſay, Peace, and ſafety, ſudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction cometh upon them, as travel upon a Woman with Child, and they ſhall not eſcape. Mark this, young one, thou mayſt flatter thy ſelf, ſaying, thou ſhalt have peace and mercy, but thou art never the better for flattering thy ſelf, for this will not help thee to eſcape; nay, thou art the worſe, for thou art in the greater danger: For when is the time that deſtruction cometh? The Text anſwers it, and tells you, the deſtruction cometh, when they flatter themſelves with falſe peace. The Man in the Goſpel promiſed himſelf many years, but God brands him for a Fool for it; <hi>This Night ſhall thy Soul be required of thee?</hi> Who ſhall require his Soul? the Devils, they come and claim him, becauſe he is theirs, not having an intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt. Take him, Devils: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, take this Chriſtleſs Soul, away to Hell with it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It will be irrecoverable danger: If thou art taken by Death out of Chriſt thy danger is irrecoverable, thou ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt upon a ſtate that is unchangeable: that is, if thou haſt not got a Chriſt then, there will be no getting him for ever: there will be no change of your ſtate for ever: if then Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, you ſhall be for ever Chriſtleſs; therefore it is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98775:9"/>
thing to be found out of Chriſt: Young one, conſider and lay it to heart, <hi>Job</hi> 14. 14. if a Man dye, ſhall he live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? that is, If things are amiſs with him, when he dyes, ſhall he come into this World again to mend them? If a Man dyes out of Chriſt, ſhall he come again to get him? No, no; therefore ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> all my days I will wait, prepare, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for my change by Death. As the Tree falls, ſo it lies: as a Man's ſtate is, when Death comes, ſo it finds and leaves him; and as Death leaves him, ſo Judgment finds him, and ſo Sentence paſſeth upon him for ever.</p>
            <p>Then the Sinner, if it be not ſeared, and paſt feeling, will cry, Lord, give me a Chriſt, mercy; Lord, I will have a Chriſt now; let my ſins go now; Lord, now I will be godly; No, now it is too late, now the Lord proceeds to the Sentence: if the Soul be in Chriſt, happy is it; then the Sentence is, <hi>Come ye bleſſed enter into the Kingdom:</hi> if the Soul be out of Chriſt, then miſerable for ever; then the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is, <hi>Depart Curſed, into Everlaſting Fire, with the Devil and his Angels,</hi> Mat. 25. 41. Depart from me; O this is dreadful, though the Sinner doth not value God's preſence now, it will be for his preſence then: O Lord, thy preſence is the only happineſs; I had better never have been born, than ſhut out of thy preſence: Lord, if I muſt depart from thee, bleſs me before I go; No, <hi>depart Curſed,</hi> curſed: Lord, if I muſt depart, let me go into ſome good place; No, <hi>depart Curſed into Everlaſting Fire:</hi> Lord, then let me have ſome good Company; No, <hi>depart with the Devil and his Angels:</hi> Devils and Damned Wretches ſhall be your Companions: You were not for the Company of the Godly in the World, but were for the Company of the Wicked; therefore De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils and Damned ones ſhall be your Company in Hell: then you will cry, But, Lord, if I muſt go to ſuch a miſerable place, and Company, let it be but for a little time; No, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part Curſed into Everlaſting Fire:</hi> You were never weary of ſinning, therefore there ſhall never be end of your miſery: Oh this word will break the heart! never! never! never! You ſhall burn, and be tormented; burn, and roar; burn and howl, ever! ever! ever! <hi>There the Worm dyeth not, there the Fire is not quenched,</hi> Mark 9. 43, 44.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98775:10"/>
O therefore, young ones, look about you, and labour to get a Chriſt while you may: is not this good news, that there is yet a Chriſt to be had? What would the Damned give to hear ſuch news as this? what would they give? They would give ten thouſand Worlds if they had them for one offer of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>O what a prize haſt thou put into thy Hands! Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers himſelf to thee in the miniſtry of his Word: He calls thee by his Goſpel: He beſeeches thee to come to him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. He promiſes graciouſly to receive thee: Stands with open Arms ready to embrace thee, if thou wilt come, <hi>John</hi> 6. 37. He waits for thy coming, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30 18. Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects your coming now; complains of your not coming, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 21. Mat. 23. 37. Nay, Chriſt mourns, and grieves, when you come not, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 41, 42. Young one, Chriſt looks for thy coming at this call: Wilt thou diſappoint him? Wilt thou put him to grief? You will not grieve a dear Friend: And will you grieve ſuch a Friend as Chriſt is, who would ſave you from Hell? It is more then all the deareſt, and beſt Friends you have in the World can do for you; and will you grieve him? Remember, this will grieve you at laſt, and torment you too: When God himſelf ſhall come and plead againſt you, as <hi>Pſalm</hi> 81. 10, 11. I would have ſaved you; but ye would not: Think (Soul) how this will torment thee: O! Chriſt would have ſaved me; but I would not be ſaved! Chriſt would have pitied me; but I would not pity my ſelf! I would have my Will, tho' I have woe! I would not be ſaved! I would be damned! O that I had never been born! O that I had been a Dog, a Toad, any thing in the World, rather then a Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man! Ah Soul! away to Chriſt: never bring ſuch torment upon thy ſelf by refuſing Jeſus Chriſt. If thou go Chriſtleſs after all this, take notice of theſe five Aggravations more, that will attend thy Miſery.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The offers of Chriſt will exceedingly aggravate thy Miſery. This will torment thee to conſider, Chriſt offered himſelf to me, and I would not have him: Chriſt called af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me, and I mad wretch would not: I would none of his Counſels, I would not chuſe the fear of the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98775:10"/>
20, to 30. Chriſt knock'd at my Door, and I would not open to him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 20. Oh horrour! horrour! horrour!</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Promiſes, and threatnings of the Goſpel will lie againſt you: Chriſt in the Goſpel promiſes Salvation to you, if you will come to him; threatens Damnation upon your not coming, <hi>John</hi> 3. 16, 18, 19. <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 16. Now this will torment thee, that none of theſe would prevail with thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The incoms of other young Ones will lie againſt thee: Other young Ones of your Brothers, Siſters, or play fellows, have heard and obeyed the voice of Chriſt, and come in to him; and you ſtood it out in the hardneſs of your Hearts: They have left their Pleaſures, and Vanities; and have giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en up themſelves to Chriſt's Holy Ways; they endured the Mocks, and Scoffs, and Reproaches of the World; but you would not, and therefore muſt be the laughing-ſtock of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils for ever. O how will this torment you, to think ſuch, ſuch ones, came in to Chriſt; ſuch young Ones are got into Heaven, and I am ſhut out; I am tormented in theſe flames! <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 8. Luk. 16. 22, 23, 24, 25.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Blood of Chriſt will lie againſt you. O tremble to think of it! It will be a dreadful thing for the Blood of Chriſt to cry againſt thee! This hath a loud Cry: God told <hi>Cain,</hi> Gen. 4. 10. <hi>The Voice of thy Brother's Blood cryeth to me:</hi> If the Blood of <hi>Abel</hi> cried ſo loud againſt <hi>Cain,</hi> that he cried out hideouſly, My puniſhment is greater than I can bear; how terrible will be the cry of the Blood of Chriſt againſt thee? If thou comeſt not into Chriſt, thou art a Murderer of him. When <hi>Peter</hi> told his Hearers of it, <hi>They were pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at the Heart,</hi> Acts 2. 36, 37. Oh, Soul, old or young, may this prick thy Heart now, and drive thee to Chriſt: This will be thy Eternal Mercy: But if it doth not; it will be thy Eternal Miſery. If thou refuſeſt Jeſus Chriſt, thou art not only a Murderer of him; a Crucifier of Chriſt again; as if it were not enough that he was crucified once, but that he muſt be crucified again by you, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 6. But thou art a trampler upon the Blood of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 28, 29. If Chriſt ſhould come in Perſon, viſibly to you; and ſhould tell you, you are a Sinner, and muſt periſh for ever, if you have not a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and there is none in Heaven, or Earth, can help you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98775:11"/>
my ſelf: But alas poor Soul, I pity thee, my Bowels yern towards thee, O come unto me, here is my Blood, my Love, my Benefits, Heaven, and Glory, all thine: And now thou ſhouldeſt (inſtead of admiring his Grace, Love and cloſing with him,) take him, and Spit in his Face, Buffet him, Trample upon him: Now, Soul, Young or Old, this is the very Caſe: Chriſt, in his infinite Pity, offers Himſelf, his Blood, his Love to thee, a poor ſinking, periſhing Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and if thou refuſeſt him, this is the very Sence, the very Judgment, that God himſelf makes of thy refuſal; and he hath ſet it down in this Text, upon Record; thou tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt under foot the Blood of the Son of God: Mark far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what will be thy Puniſhment for this Sin; He that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law died without Mercy; how much ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Puniſhment ſhall he have, that hath troden under foot the Blood of Chriſt? You ſhall have a ſorer Puniſhment then he that hath ſinned againſt <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law: He died without Mercy; yet you ſhall have a ſorer Judgment: What will that be? Enough (one ſhould think) to fright the Sinner out of his Sins to Chriſt: It is certain, it will be woful; but Mark farther ſtill, what follows, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 30. <hi>Vengeance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to me, I will recompence, ſaith the Lord.</hi> O tremble at this Sin of refuſing Chriſt. It cries, Vengeance, Vengeance, Vengeance againſt the Chriſtleſs Soul: The Unbeliever tramples upon the Blood of Chriſt; and Vengeance ſhall fall upon him that tramples on it. Ah Soul, away to Chriſt; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver let the Blood of Chriſt cry againſt thee.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Miniſters of Chriſt will come againſt you, if you be found out of Chriſt. God hath made his Miniſters Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, for to beſeech Sinners to come in to Chriſt, and they muſt return an Anſwer of their Embaſſage to their Lord, and Maſter; and if you come nor in, they muſt come, and bear witneſs againſt you, that they delivered their Meſſage, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19, 20. Therefore what will you ſay for your ſelf in that Day: You cannot ſay, Chriſt was not offered to you: No, you will be ſpeechleſs, when the Lord asks the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, How cameſt thou without a Wedding Garment? How come you to be without the Righteouſneſs of my Son, was it not offered you? Then I muſt come, and witneſs againſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98775:11"/>
you; Yea Lord, I offered him to this Sinner; this young Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, this old Sinner: God hath made us Watchmen to give you warning of the danger of your Souls without a Chriſt; and if we give you not warning, God will require your Blood at our Hands; but if we give you warning, and you come not, your Blood will lye upon your own Heads, and we have delivered our Souls, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 4, to 9. As <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Servant ſaid to him, when he ſent him, to get a Wife for his Son <hi>Iſaac;</hi> but if the Woman will not come? Then, ſaith he, thou ſhalt be free from thine Oath: So here, God ſwears us Miniſters, to preach his Goſpel, to offer his Son Jeſus to be Married to poor Sinners; and we endeavour to woe for Chriſt, to get a Wife for our Maſter's Son; and would fain have you come, and match with our Lord Jeſus; but if you will not, we are free from our Oath, and your Blood will lye upon your own Heads: Now, Soul, let me plead with thee; and not only plead, but prevail with thee: Here is a rich Match, a glorious Match; all the World, Heaven, and Earth cannot afford ſuch another Match, and wilt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe him? As <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Servant offered all his Maſter's Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; my Maſter hath great Riches, Flocks, and Herds; Camels, and Aſſes; Silver, and Gold; and all for his Son <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac:</hi> So I ſay to thee; my Lord and Maſter hath great Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, unſearchable Riches; both Worlds are his; and all entailed upon his Son Jeſus; come, Soul, and Match with him, and All ſhall be thine: Doth not all this win thy Heart? Oh! what a grief will this be to us Miniſters, that are willing to ſpend, and be ſpent for you; could willingly beg upon our Knees to perſwade you; yea, even lay down our Hearts Blood to gain you; rather than to come at laſt to witneſs againſt you? Ah! Sweet Soul, conſider theſe things ſeriouſly; let not theſe Aggravations lye upon thee: Come, and give up thy ſelf to Chriſt for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> Some Soul may Object, and ſay; Oh but, I am too great a Sinner; I am afraid, I may not come to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Thy Sins are not greater then Chriſt is a Saviour: Though thy Sins are great, his Merits are greater: Though
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98775:12"/>
thy Sins are many, his Mercies are more: Though thy Sins abound, his Grace ſuperabounds, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 18. God ſaith, Come, and <hi>though your Sins are as Scarlet, they ſhall be as white as Snow:</hi> If they are never ſo many and never ſo great; if you are willing to part with them; Come, ſaith Chriſt, I will multiply to pardon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 7. What if thy Sins are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great; if his Mercies are greater? If thy Sins are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo many, if his Mercies are more? all this cannot hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee of Chriſt, if thou wilt come. O therefore come, and thy Sins ſhall not hinder thy acceptance: Though thy Sins have weakned the Law, and made that unable to ſave thee; yet they have not weakened Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3, 4. Chriſt is able to ſave to the uttermoſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25, 26. If thou ſeeſt more Sins ſtill, and ſtill more and more, yet he is able to ſave to the uttermoſt. Chriſt is able to the uttermoſt of your Sins; and to the uttermoſt of your Doubts and Fears. Neither Quality, nor Quantity of your Sins can poſe Chriſt: There is not ſo much evil in all thy Sins, as there is fulneſs in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 9. 23. If thou canſt believe, the Pardon of all thy Sins is poſſible. Chriſt can drown Mountains, as well as Mole-hills.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> You may Object, and ſay; but I am afraid, Chriſt is not willing to ſave me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Chriſt is as willing, as able to ſave thee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 2, 3. A Leper comes to Chriſt, <hi>Lord, if thou wilt, thou canſt make me clean:</hi> Chriſt Anſwers at next Word, <hi>I will, be thou clean:</hi> As if Chriſt had ſaid, Do you Queſtion my willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? I would have you know, that I am as willing, as able. <hi>And immediately he was cleanſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But you will ſay; I am unworthy Chriſt ſhould look upon me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. A worthineſs of your own is not expected; nor required: Nor will you be rejected for want of a worthineſs of your own. God never ſaid to any, If you be ſo and ſo worthy, come to me; but, Come, and believe in Chriſt for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98775:12"/>
worthineſs. You are to come to Chriſt for worthineſs: And when you are come to Chriſt, all his worthineſs is yours, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. 7, 12, 13. <hi>I ſaid after all theſe, turn unto me:</hi> As if the Lord had ſaid, come unto me, art thou never ſuch a Sinner, and art never ſo unworthy: Only acknowledge thy unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and be willing to be beholding to me for worthineſs; and I will marry thee: And then if thou wert never ſo unworthy in thy ſelf, thou art worthy in Chriſt: And wert thou never ſo Poor in thy ſelf, thou wilt be Rich in Chriſt: And wert thou never ſo vile in thy ſelf, thou wilt be righteous in Chriſt: For he hath a worthineſs, on purpoſe to make thee worthy: He hath a Righteouſneſs, on purpoſe to make thee Righteous, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21. O then thou muſt needs be worthy, for then thou wilt have the Righteouſneſs of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 25, 26. Chriſt hath the Righteouſneſs of God, on purpoſe to give to Poor Sinners, that go to him: And when thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveſt on him, thou haſt his Righteouſneſs; and God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be juſt, if he doth not juſtifie thee.</p>
            <p>2. If you pretend to a worthineſs of your own, it is reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14. 4. God ſaith, <hi>I will heal your backſlidings, and Love you freely:</hi> If God will Love freely, what can hinder? What can hinder Free-Grace? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43. 25. <hi>I will blot out your Iniquities for my Name's-ſake:</hi> God gives Chriſt, and his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, for his Name's ſake; for his Free-Grace ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 6. It is of Grace, not of Works; it is of Grace, not of Worthineſs of yours.</p>
            <p>3. An humble Sence of your unworthineſs is accepted, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. 7. Chriſt accepts for his Name's-ſake, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 18, 19, 20. The Prodigal had ſpent all his Stock, had no Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, comes ragged, and torn; but it was in his Heart to come home to his Father; his Father ſees him afar off, runs to meet him; he was ſo eager to ſhew Mercy, he could not ſtay till he came; he runs to meet him; falls on his Neck, and kiſſes him. Chriſt gives us this Parable, to ſhew his readineſs to ſhew Mercy to Poor Sinners, upon their coming to him. O what a Father is here? Eyes full of Mercy, he ſees him afar off: Legs full of Mercy, he runs to meet him: Arms full of Mercy, he embraces him: Lips full of Mercy, he Kiſſes him: An Heart full of Mercy, he calls
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98775:13"/>
for the Robe, and Ring, and Fatted Calf: He doth not think the beſt Robe, nor the beſt Dainties too good for him. Thus will the Lord Jeſus do for thee, if thou wilt go to him: He will not think the beſt Robe, nor En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment too good for thee: Thou ſhalt have his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, blood, love; and then thou wilt be worthy in Chriſt; beautiful, exceeding Beautiful in him, yea, perfect through his comelineſs, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 6, 8, to 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> O, but I am not only unworthy, but unfit for Chriſt, if I could find any change in my heart, more power over my corruptions, or were more holy; then I could dare to go to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt. The firſt gift that God gives to Sinners is Chriſt, and himſelf in Chriſt: he doth not firſt give grace to change the heart, and then give Chriſt; but gives Chriſt and grace with him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God doth not expect you ſhould bring to him, but come and receive from him, you do not carry Phyſick to the Doctor, nor water to the Fountain, but you go to them for them: you go with your empty Pitcher to the Well for Water, you muſt go as a poor naked Sinner to Chriſt for Righteouſneſs, and as a poor empty Soul to Chriſt for grace: You muſt go to Chriſt as you are, and he will take you, and fit you for himſelf: So Chriſt invites you to come to him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 1. He that is athirſt, ſees his need of him; hath a mind to him; let him come; though he hath no money, no merit, no righteouſneſs, nor goodneſs, let him come, and take all of me, <hi>without money, and without price:</hi> Soul, thou needeſt not fear being rejected, becauſe thou haſt no righteouſneſs of thy own, for here is no price ſet: Chriſt offers all this <hi>without money, and without price.</hi> Away then doubting Soul to Jeſus Chriſt; and he is certainly thine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Appointment of Chriſt is for thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 12, 13. He will not refuſe thee becauſe thou art a Sinner, for he came on purpoſe for Sinners: If thou hadſt a Righteouſneſs he were not for thee, but if thou ſeeſt thy ſelf to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98775:13"/>
be a Sinner, and that thou haſt no Righteouſneſs of thy own, then thou art the Soul that Chriſt is for, he ſeeks for ſuch as thou art.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Promiſe of Chriſt: The Offer and Promiſe of Chriſt are for thee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28. Art thou a burthened Soul? Is Sin the burthen of thy Soul, and life? Will nothing ſatisfie thy Soul but a Chriſt? Then be of good comfort, riſe, go, he calleth thee, <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 49. And he promiſeth to receive thee, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 37. he will in no wiſe, in no hand, caſt thee out. Doth not this revive thee?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Art thou diſtreſſed for Chriſt? Is thy heart towards him? Be of good comfort, the heart of Chriſt is towards thee, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 14. Go to him, he will ſpeak to thy heart, he will ſpeak a comfortable word to thee, that will do thee good at heart. And he tells thee further, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. he will betroth thee, he will marry thee, he will, he will: The Reaſon is in that word loving kindneſs, which ſignifies bowels: His bowels are towards thee, he cannot reject thee: Nay, further, his Soul is in travel for thee, troubled Soul, that art in travel for him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 11. here is enough for thee; go, believe on him, venture thy Soul on him, and he is thine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> O but I cannot believe: I can no more believe, than create a World: I ſee I muſt believe, or I am damned; and I ſee I cannot believe, though I be damned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is well if thou art come to this: God brings no Soul to this, but he gives them Faith, and Chriſt: Thou muſt go to God for Faith, as well as for Chriſt: Faith is his gift, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 29. God gives to believe, therefore go, and fall down at the foot of God, cry to him for Chriſt, cry to him for Faith; God never did, nor never will deny faith to any Soul that ſeriouſly asks him for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> I have prayed, and ſought Chriſt, but know not yet whether he will receive me, or not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98775:14"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Pray, and ſeek him ſtill; believe that he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, He hath promiſed it, and will make his word good. He cannot nor will not fail, he will not fail of his promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 33, 34, 35. he ſaith, his Covenant, his Promiſe he will not break, he will not lye: If God breaks his Promiſe, he lyes. Nay, he cannot fail, he cannot lye, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 15. Though we are full of unbelievings, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings of heart, yet he abideth faithful, and cannot deny himſelf: Doubting Soul, therefore thou art ſure of Chriſt if thou continueſt praying, and lying at the foot of God for him; for he hath promiſed him to ſeeking Souls, and cannot deny himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, He hath performed it to others. God hath given Chriſt to ſeeking Souls; therefore lay all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and come to Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Believe: Will you queſtion, and have the truth of God for it? His Promiſe, and his Oath, two immutable things, wherein it is impoſſible for God to lye? One immutable thing is enough; had you only God's word for it, it were enough, being unchangeable; but you have two immutable things, his Promiſe, and Oath too; and all this, that you may be ſtrong in Believing. <hi>He that Believes not, makes God a Lyar,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 10. Will you dare to make God a Lyar? Indeed God will be true, whether we believe him, or not; but as much as in us lies, we make him a Lyar: Well, you have God's Promiſe, and Oath too, to receive you, if you come in to Chriſt; O therefore believe; yea, away to Chriſt, be ſtrong in believing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wait: Waiting Souls have found Chriſt, <hi>Mary</hi> weeps, and waits at the Sepulchre, and Chriſt ſhews himſelf to her, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 11, 15, 16. There are ſome Souls that have been under the hidings of Chriſt ſeveral years; yet continuing ſeeking, and waiting, have found him at laſt. Therefore, ſeek, believe, and wait, though Chriſt doth not come pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98775:14"/>
1 Firſt, His heart is towards thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 18, 19, 20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, It is for Chriſt's intereſt to receive thee, he looſeth his blood elſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 11. and Chriſt will not loſe his blood, now it is ſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Chriſt is faithful, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 17, 18. Chriſt is faithful in his Office; now it is his Office to ſave Souls; and he would not be faithful, if he ſhould not ſave the Souls that come to him: Away to Chriſt then, and you are ſure to be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. The laſt Uſe is to Believers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, For Conſolation. Here is comfort for Believers indeed; you have ſought and found Chriſt; your danger is paſt, as to Death, Judgment, Hell, and all miſery; you are ſecured for Eternity: O what would the Damned in Hell give to be in your Condition? You have the Pearl of great price. You have him that is more worth than ten thouſand Worlds. Happy are the Souls that are in ſuch a caſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For Direction to Believers: Do not you ſay, What ſhall we do to anſwer theſe mercies?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, Admire the Infinite Grace, and love of Chriſt to your Souls: You cannot ſufficiently admire, but you are to be admiring. O admire, and ſtill admire; and be ſwallowed up in the admiration of this grace! Cry out with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 3. 18, 19. O the heighth, and length, and depth and breadth of this grace! <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 33. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, he ſought you firſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 1. You would have never ſought him, if he had not ſought you firſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 19. <hi>We love him, becauſe he firſt loved us.</hi> O this firſt love is to be admired! <hi>He choſe you before the World was:</hi> He loved you from everlaſting. O admire it!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, He inclined your hearts to ſeek him: You would have been ſeekers after ſin, and vanity, not Chriſt, if he had not inclin'd your hearts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, God gave you Faith to lay hold on Chriſt, or elſe you would have been Unbelievers, as well as others, all you have, is of grace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 7. your juſtification,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98775:15"/>
adoption, glorification; all grace: And that you ſhould be partakers of this grace, when ſo many of your friends, neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are left out. O cry, grace, grace, <hi>John</hi> 14. 22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Not only admire, but exceedingly love Jeſus Chriſt: O how dearly ſhould you love him, who hath ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you, as to ſhed his blood, and dye for you, <hi>John</hi> 15. 13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 7.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Live Chriſt. Not only love Chriſt, but live Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 14. Let this love of Chriſt conſtrain you, to live to him, who dyed for you. <hi>What manner of Perſons ought you to be in all holy Converſation, and Godlineſs?</hi> 2. Pet. 3. 11, 14. O take heed of doing any thing that ſhall diſpleaſe this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Chriſt, or diſhonour this precious Chriſt. O labour to pleaſe this precious Chriſt, labour to exalt, and glorifie him: Let hearts, and lives, glorifie him. Let us, and ours glorifie him; who is worthy of all Honour, and Glory, Majeſty, and Dominion; for ever, and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS Printed for</hi> Thomas Parkhurſt <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns, <hi>the Lower end of</hi> Cheapſide.</head>
            <p>THE Church's Triumph over Death, a Funeral Sermon Preached upon the Deceaſe of Bleſſed Mr. <hi>Robert Fleming,</hi> Late Paſtor of a Church in <hi>Rotterdam.</hi> By <hi>Daniel Burgeſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Grand Queſtion Reſolved, what we muſt do to be Saved. Inſtructions for a Holy Life.</p>
            <p>A Call to Seriouſneſs in Religion.</p>
            <p>Good Counſel to the Converted and Unconverted: To make Death ſafe, Sickneſs Profitable, Death Comfortable to themſelves, and that Sickneſs Inſtructive to others. Alſo ſome Directions to the Friends of the Sick, that are about them. And a Form of Exhortation to the Ungodly in their Sickneſs, <hi>Or thoſe that we fear are ſuch.</hi> Together with a Form of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to the Godly in their Sickneſs.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
